Defensive Mind
I would like to ask about relationships.
Married at 27, now I am 55 years old.
We have one child, 28 years old.
We've been separated for about 10 years.
It was due to some problems
in my husband's family.
I learned through my child that
my husband wants to end this marriage,
since he now has another person.
So, I went to see him
to settle the matter.
Although I wanted to hear
his side of the story first,
he asked me to tell him about how I felt.
As I was talking to him,
he brought up his right as a parent.
In my view, he was not very
involved in our child's upbringing.
He was always rather
self-absorbed.
So, when I heard him asserting
his right as a parent,
I became irate and just
stormed out of the place.
Since that day, I have been
thinking about relationships.
How do I conclude this relationship
well enough so that I won't suffer?
How do I make sure that
my child doesn't suffer?
It has been about a month already
but I am not able to do much of anything.
Meeting other people arouses
my defensive attitude.
I would like to finish this
relationship skillfully.
I suggest you offer the
prayers of repentance
and of gratitude to your husband.
Don't think about yourself.
"How difficult it has been for you
to live with a woman like me."
"How else could this be happening?
I am really sorry."
Regardless whether you get a divorce
or not, do this prayer for 100 days.
First do this repentance
prayer for 100 days.
Then, whether your relationship
continues or not,
a resolution will be reached so that your
new life with someone else may also work.
If you divorced him in the middle
of this conflict of resentment,
should your husband die in an accident,
or something happens,
though you may consider it OK,
but you would feel guilty
and you would regret.
"I should have listened to
him better then,"
You would regret with such thoughts.
So, you must repent not for him but for yourself.
Through the prayers, you would be
healed of the wounds you received from him
(Sunim) Do you understand?
Yes, I do.
Then, you will not feel guilty if
and when you get married again.
There will be no jealousy
when he gets remarried.
You would have done everything even if
he would die, or things work out well.
You would become free of him.
To be completely free of him, you need to
offer the prayer for 100 days.
Then, you will reach a resolution.
So, without regard to the legal issues,
do the repentance prayer first.
Second, your husband
is your child's father.
Whether he helped raise the child or not,
or he was involved or not, he has
a parental right as a father.
This, you must acknowledge.
Being respectful of the father's right,
you ought to say to your child,
"Go ahead and see your father."
"Be mindful of what he tells you."
you must give your child
the opportunities to be close to him
This would be good for whom?
Your child.
So, don't look upon
your husband with hatred.
Respect him as a father.
Even though your relationship
with him is over,
respecting his role as a father
will be good for your child.
Though you are divorced,
you child must not suffer.
Our child is very confused now,
so I asked my husband to discuss
with me to find the solutions.
I asked him not to involve our child
since she is rather confused.
(Sunim) No, that is not the way to go.
(Sunim) How old is your child?
She is 28 years old.
28 years old is an adult. She and he have
the right to communicate directly.
Don't think that they must go through you.
(Questioner) But he discusses
things about me with her.
Your husband can discuss
whatever he wants with her.
You can tell him to discuss the matters
concerning you only with you.
It is up to him
how he deals with his child.
You child will deal with
him in her own way.
If you child mentions
something her father said,
"No need for you to worry about.
My issues, I will deal with them myself."
You can suggest that he keeps his
communication with her on her issues,
and not discuss your issues with her. You
can tell him this without getting angry.
If you continue your prayer of
repentance, this will be done naturally.
(Questioner) How shall I pray?
What sort of recitation in prayers?
You are a bit stubborn, aren't you?
Yes, I am stubborn.
(Sunim) You get very angry also, right?
I don't get angry often
but when I do I lose control.
(Sunim) Can't control yourself, right?
Do you think your husband enjoyed
living with a woman with such temper?
So, you could say, "Honey, I am so sorry.
You must have been so frustrated with me."
"I am stubborn and have a fiery temper."
"You could have faired much better
with a gentler woman."
"I am sorry that you suffered
a lot because of me."
How long have you lived with him?
(Questioner) About 28 years.
But we lived apart for 10 years
(Questioner) so we lived
together for 18 years or so
Your husband lived with you for 18 years.
(Questioner) yes.
Wow, he stayed a long time with you.
If it were me, I couldn't last 3 years.
"I am grateful that you
stayed with me for 18 years."
(Sunim) This is how you
pray reciting these words.
I understand. Thank you.